<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="es"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ornelavaldez.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ornelavaldez.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="es"/><updated>2025-01-07T02:41:29+00:00</updated><id>https://ornelavaldez.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ornela Valdez</title><subtitle>Ornela Valdez </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Bridging the Gap - Ximena Peredo’s Journey from Activism to Collaborative Politics</title><link href="https://ornelavaldez.github.io//blog/2023/Bridging-the-gap/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bridging the Gap - Ximena Peredo’s Journey from Activism to Collaborative Politics"/><published>2023-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ornelavaldez.github.io//blog/2023/Bridging-the-gap</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ornelavaldez.github.io//blog/2023/Bridging-the-gap/"><![CDATA[<div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Ximena-Peredo-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Ximena-Peredo-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Ximena-Peredo-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Ximena-Peredo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <blockquote> <p>Ximena Peredo’s story is an example of a remarkable journey, from being an activist and columnist to becoming the Secretary of Citizen Participation in Nuevo León, Mexico, where she pioneers collaborative and open governance models. Peredo’s approach challenges traditional political paradigms, emphasizing the transformative power collaborative decision-making in healing the relationship between government and civil society.</p> </blockquote> <p>In the realm of modern politics, where courage, trust, and ethical leadership are often elusive, Ximena Peredo’s journey from activism to politics stands as a testament to the transformative power of inclusive governance. As the Secretary of Citizen Participation for the state government of Nuevo Leon in Mexico, Peredo and her team have been instrumental in reshaping the narrative around citizen engagement and collaborative decision-making.</p> <p><strong>A Surprising Honor</strong></p> <p>Ximena Peredo recently received the Democratic Innovators of the 21st Century Award, Politicians’ Hall of Fame, announced at the Athens Democracy Forum in association with Apolitical Foundation, thanks to the postulation that Auna, a platform that promotes new political representations with women’s leadership, made acknowledging the potential of Ximena and other women to bring positive and innovative change in the realm of politics.</p> <p><strong>From Activism to Politics</strong></p> <p>Peredo’s transition from activism to politics was far from expected. Initially an activist and columnist, she entered the political arena during the 2021 elections when she ran for deputy. Motivated by a desire to address the diminishing influence of citizens in public decisions, Peredo accepted the challenge to become the first Secretary of the newly established Ministry of Citizen Participation in Nuevo Leon, invited by the elected governor Samuel García.</p> <p><strong>Breaking Down Barriers</strong></p> <p>The establishment of the Ministry of Citizen Participation faced initial resistance, both within Peredo’s team and in societal perceptions that government and civil society were inherently adversarial. Peredo and her team now work hard to emphasize the importance of bridging this gap and dispelling the myth that these entities are fundamentally opposed.</p> <p><strong>Navigating the Complexities</strong></p> <p>Peredo acknowledges the complexity of the processes and the need for incremental steps. The Ministry of Citizen Participation focuses on building internal capacities within the government and straightening and facilitating civic spaces with civil society organizations and other activists to activate citizen participation. She underscores the importance of developing methodologies that facilitate genuine dialogue between the government and the people.</p> <p><strong>Rebuilding Trust</strong></p> <p>Rebuilding trust with civil society, particularly with assiduous activists, poses a significant challenge. In the A political Hope Podcast episode where Ximena is interviewed, she shares personal experiences of facing skepticism from former supporters who perceived her transition into politics as a betrayal of her activist roots. She emphasizes the ongoing process of rebuilding relationships and gaining credibility.</p> <p><strong>Feminine Leadership in Politics</strong></p> <p>Peredo introduces a unique perspective on feminine leadership in politics, noting that as more women enter politics, a shift occurs from a competitive and adversarial approach to a collaborative and supportive one. This shift is characterized by complimenting colleagues, building alliances, and recognizing the collective intelligence that diverse perspectives bring to the table.</p> <p><strong>A Call to Action</strong></p> <p>Peredo’s testimony is a powerful message to fellow activists, urging them to step into politics without fear of losing their personal principles. She encourages a new form of activism—working within the government to bring about positive change. The call is clear: government needs people who understand the power of citizen anger and activism.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tendiendo un puente - el camino de Ximena Peredo desde el activismo hacia una política más colaborativa</title><link href="https://ornelavaldez.github.io//blog/2023/Tendiendo-un-puente/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tendiendo un puente - el camino de Ximena Peredo desde el activismo hacia una política más colaborativa"/><published>2023-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ornelavaldez.github.io//blog/2023/Tendiendo-un-puente</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ornelavaldez.github.io//blog/2023/Tendiendo-un-puente/"><![CDATA[<div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Ximena-Peredo-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Ximena-Peredo-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Ximena-Peredo-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Ximena-Peredo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <blockquote> <p>La historia de Ximena Peredo es un ejemplo de una notable trayectoria, desde ser una activista y columnista hasta convertirse en la Secretaria de Participación Ciudadana en Nuevo León, México, donde lidera modelos de gobierno colaborativos y abiertos. El enfoque de Peredo desafía los paradigmas políticos tradicionales, haciendo hincapié en el poder transformador de la toma de decisiones colaborativa para sanar la relación entre el gobierno y la sociedad civil.</p> </blockquote> <p>En el ámbito de la política moderna, donde la valentía, la confianza y el liderazgo ético a menudo son esquivos, el viaje de Ximena Peredo desde el activismo hasta la política es un testimonio del poder transformador de un gobierno inclusivo. Como Secretaria de Participación Ciudadana del gobierno estatal de Nuevo León en México, Peredo y su equipo han sido fundamentales para reformar la narrativa en torno a la participación ciudadana y la toma de decisiones colaborativa.</p> <p><strong>Un Honor Inesperado</strong></p> <p>Ximena Peredo recibió recientemente el Premio a los Innovadores Democráticos del Siglo XXI, Salón de la Fama de los Políticos, anunciado en el Foro de Democracia de Atenas en asociación con The Apolitical Foundation, gracias a la postulación que realizó Auna, una plataforma que promueve nuevas representaciones políticas con liderazgo femenino, reconociendo el potencial de Ximena y otras mujeres para generar un cambio positivo e innovador en el ámbito político.</p> <p><strong>Del Activismo a la Política</strong></p> <p>La transición de Peredo del activismo a la política no era de esperarse. Inicialmente activista y columnista, ingresó al ámbito político durante las elecciones de 2021 cuando se postuló para diputada. Motivada por el deseo de abordar la falta de incidencia de los ciudadanos en las decisiones públicas, Peredo aceptó el desafío de convertirse en la primera Secretaria de la recién creada Secretaría de Participación Ciudadana en Nuevo León, invitada por el gobernador electo Samuel García.</p> <p><strong>Rompiendo Barreras</strong></p> <p>El establecimiento de la Secretaría de Participación Ciudadana enfrentó una resistencia inicial, tanto dentro del equipo de Ximena como en las percepciones sociales de que el gobierno y la sociedad civil eran inherentemente adversarios. Peredo y su equipo ahora trabajan arduamente para enfatizar la importancia de cerrar esta brecha y desmentir el mito de que estas entidades son fundamentalmente opuestas.</p> <p><strong>Navegando las Complejidades</strong></p> <p>Peredo reconoce la complejidad de los procesos y la necesidad de pasos incrementales. La Secretaría de Participación Ciudadana se enfoca en desarrollar capacidades al interior del gobierno y en fortalecer y facilitar espacios cívicos con organizaciones de la sociedad civil y otras personas activistas para activar la participación ciudadana. Ella destaca la importancia de desarrollar metodologías que faciliten el diálogo genuino entre el gobierno y la población.</p> <p><strong>Reconstruyendo la Confianza</strong></p> <p>Reconstruir la confianza con la sociedad civil, especialmente con activistas asiduos, representa un desafío significativo. En el episodio del podcast “A Political Hope” donde Ximena es entrevistada, nos comparte experiencias personales de enfrentar escepticismo de antiguos seguidores que percibieron su transición a la política como una traición a sus raíces activistas. Ella enfatiza el proceso continuo de reconstruir relaciones y ganar credibilidad.</p> <p><strong>Liderazgo Femenino en la Política</strong></p> <p>Peredo introduce una perspectiva única sobre el liderazgo femenino en la política, señalando que a medida que más mujeres ingresan a la política, se produce el cambio del usual enfoque competitivo y adversarial a uno colaborativo y de apoyo. Esta transformación se caracteriza por elogiar a los colegas, construir alianzas y reconocer la inteligencia colectiva que aportan perspectivas diversas.</p> <p><strong>Un Llamado a la Acción</strong></p> <p>El testimonio de Peredo es un mensaje poderoso para sus compañeras y compañeros activistas, instándolos a ingresar a la política sin temor a perder sus principios personales. Ella fomenta una nueva forma de activismo: trabajar dentro del gobierno para lograr un cambio positivo. El llamado es claro: el gobierno necesita personas que comprendan el poder de la ira y el activismo ciudadano.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>